ESCAPE THE MORNING

Poul Anderson

Troubles never come singly, or Mark Jordan would not have been racing the sunrise for his life.

It had begun as just a pleasant bit of excitement. He was on watch in the communications room. Someone had to be there all the time when they were at home. Emergencies on the Moon have a way of arriving fast and nasty. But in the normal course of events, whichever of them stood by was free to tend to private matters—read, study, fool around with a hobby, or work out in the gymnasium corner of the big plastic-faced chamber. Mark had finished his calculus assignment and was on the homemade exercycle. With gravity one-sixth as strong as it is on Earth, you must spend at least two hours out of the twenty-four keeping fit, or your very bones will atrophy.

Through the whirr of the machine, the rustle of air from the ventilator ducts, his own quick breath, he got the buzz. His heart jumped. He sprang to the Visor panel. Meters stared like goblin eyes at a tall sandyhaired eighteen-year-old flipping switches. The screen came to life with Derek van Hulst’s middle-aged face.

“Copernicus to Jordan Station,” the Dutchman said. “Oh, you. Hello, Mark. Can you take a stranded man in?”

“Sure. Plenty of supplies, and choice of guestrooms.” Mark grinned. He not only did not begrudge the rations—like all pioneers, the Lunar colonists take for granted that anyone in distress is to be helped—but he was delighted. Here was a new person to talk to, for fourteen Earth-days!

Van Hulst surprised him. “They’re sending a ‘tank’ from Kepler to continue him on his way, so you won’t have him more than about twenty hours.”

Mark whistled. “Who is he to rate that?”

“The Minister of Technology of the Federated Congo, Achille Kamolondo. He’s been on the Moon for a couple of weeks now, inspecting the facilities. Was bound to us from Keplersburg when something crippled his vehicle. He was not sure what, when he called us.”

‘Was that wise? I mean letting a newcomer drive off alone, and this near dawn?”

“They told me, calling ahead, that he’d proved himself to be able. And he hates wasting time. So they lent him a Go-Devil.” Mark felt a bit of envy for someone who could take one of those out and travel at fifty miles an hour. A turtle, such as most people owned, would do twenty if you pushed. Of course, a Go-Devil had room for no more than a single person. “Let us not waste time either,” van Hulst said. “Sunrise is barely two hours off where he is. That’s on the Main Trace, naturally, between kilometers 321 and 322. About eighteen miles from your place, correct? On your way.”

“Yes, sir. I’ll report back when I return.” Mark switched off and left on the run, which is fast indeed on the Moon.

“Tom!” he shouted down the long, machine-humming hall. “Condition Yellow!”

His brother, two years younger, pelted from the hydroponics section where he had been tending algae. Judy, their kid sister, didn’t hear; she was in the soundproofed “classroom,” taking a Spanish lesson beamed from the school in Tycho Crater. Mark explained on the way to the lockers.

“I could go,” Tom said wistfully.

“You could,” Mark agreed, “but you’re not going to, me bucko.”

Tom didn’t argue. A station, alone in barrenness, needs a captain as much as any ship does. For all the free-and-easy affection between them, Mark was the Old Man.

Tom helped him into his undergarment and spacesuit. “Air valves, okay. Pressure, okay. Faceplate gasket, okay. . . They went through the ritual fast, yet not missing a point. The gear must be perfect. Human beings can’t survive a night temperature of 250° below Fahrenheit zero, nor can they breathe vacuum.

Leaving his helmet open, Mark cycled through the garage lock and squirmed along a gang tube into his turtle. He sealed the doors, automatically disconnecting the tube. His hands, gloved but trained, found controls as he sat down. Light blossomed in the narrow steel cell, revealing an extra seat crowded next to his among the instruments. Aft of the cabin was space for extra passengers, supplies, and life support equipment. When there • was cargo to carry, the turtle was hitched to a train of the wagons that stood in this rough-hewn cave. He did not see them through windows; even the best glass is fragile and a poor radiation shield. Television panels are better.

The solar cells topside gathered energy during the two-week Lunar day to charge every cell in the station, including those in the electric motors. Mark started off. Oblong, ugly, hull pitted by tiny meteorites, the car lumbered forth on its eight huge wheels, up the ramp and out onto the surface of the Moon.

Though he had spent most of his life here, Mark always caught his breath at sight of the night heavens. Stars and stars and stars crowded the dark, uncountable, unwinking, unbelievably bright. Earth hung halfway down the western sky, four times the size of Luna seen from itself and many times as radiant. The planet was at half phase, and its majestic turning had brought America into view. Clear weather, Mark saw; he could identify glitters on the black side which were the titanic eastern cities. Westward the plains stretched soft brown and bluish green, then the Rockies, the Pacific coast, the ocean like burnished sapphire streaked with a few white cloud masses.

Dad’s country, he thought. Mothers. My mom too, for that matter. His eyes stung a little.

The moonscape offered less. Behind him jutted the small crater beneath which Jordan Station had been dug. The slopes were half concealed by machines busily at work, and dominated by the radio-TV mast on top. Otherwise that flatland called the Oceanus Procellarum reached bare as far as he could see. Not that he saw any great distance. No air or dust scattered the Earth-shine, but the coal-like mineral crust did, so that he seemed to move in the focus of a dim blue spotlight which faded out mere yards away. The horizon was a circle of starlessness, barely three miles wide. Mark turned on the headlights. They helped some—enough, if you were used to these conditions.

He plugged his suit radio into the turtle’s. “Mark to Tom,” he said. “All systems go. I’m on my way.”

“Check,” said his brothers voice in his earplugs.

“And mate.” Mark said. He gave himself to the job of driving. Luminous stones, one per kilometer, marked this side path, as they did the Trace. Neither was a true road, only a safe route. Cosmic dust, raining down for four billion years, binding molecule to molecule in vacuum, had formed the treacherous, brittle surface of the Lunar maria.

At the Trace, he followed its roundabout path easterly for almost an hour. This near day, little traffic ever moved, and he found no sign of man except the stones and the gaunt microwave relay masts that glided by, out of darkness and back into darkness. The hum of the motor, the flutter of his own breath, deepened the silence that enclosed him. He didn’t mind. Mostly he thought about his future. He’d have to go live in the dorm at Tycho University next year, in order to take laboratory courses for an engineering degree. Well, the Station was in good shape financially, he’d hire an assistant and Tom could take over as boss . . .

The undiffused puddle of light cast by his headbeams suddenly gleamed against metal. He allowed plenty of space for low-gravity braking, even from 20 mph. The Go-Devil stood inert, a four-wheeled egg with metal curled back from several holes around the motor. Huh! Meteorite shrapnel had done that. Mark tuned his ’caster. “Hello, there,” he said into his helmet mike. “You okay?”

“Yes.” He heard fluent English with a slight French accent. “Are you my, ah, rescuer? They informed me someone would come.”

“Right-o. Do you know how to get into a turtle?”

“Pardon? Oh, yes, your kind of vehicle. Certainly I do.” Monsieur Kamolondo sounded a trifle offended. Well, he must’ve been under quite a strain, Mark thought. It’s lonesome to wait for help. And on top of the shock when that debris ripped into his engine compartment—

The Congolese stepped through the inner door of the entry lock. Frost formed on his suit, chilled by the brief exposure when he crossed from car to car. He sat down beside Mark and fumbled with his helmet. Mark helped him open it.

“But you are a boy!” he exclaimed.

He wasn’t so old himself: a large man with a face brown, intelligent, and proud. The leaders of the Congo were more aristocrats than politicians. That was inevitable, in a country still struggling up from the near savagery into which its long Time of Troubles had plunged it. Nonetheless, Mark couldn’t help bristling a little at the way those eyes regarded him.

Tm not too young to run a station,” he said, and introduced himself curtly. He gunned the motor and turned the wheel. “We’d better head right back. One hour till sunrise.”

“A station?—No, I remember. An isolated enterprise. What do you do?”

Mark decided to be friendly. “We mine copper,” he said. “Started with an underground vein of ice, but that gave out. Anyway, so much water has been gotten now that the price is way down. So Dad went in for minerals. I’ve found some oil, too, that may be worth going after when we’ve saved the capital we’d need.”

“Oil?” Kamolondo blurted.

“Sure, there’s plenty on the Moon. It’s been a hundred years ago since Hoyle theorized that petroleum wasn’t formed biologically, but by photochemical reactions in the original dust cloud that became the Solar System. Even then, they’d found heterocyclic compounds in some meteorites. Turned out he was right. Of course, the lighter fractions here have long ago escaped to space, but the cracking plant at Maurolycus makes rocket fuel from what’s left. That’s one big reason why the Moon is colonized, you know. Spaceships can leave here a lot easier than they can leave Earth, especially when we tank ’em up on the spot.”

Kamolondo stiffened. “I was merely surprised to learn of deposits in this particular neighborhood,” he said in a chill voice. “After all, I am my country’s Minister of Technology.”

Mark bit his lip. “Sorry . . . sir.”

Kamolondo made an obvious effort to unbend. “Well,” he said, “I should not expect you to be too, ah, too conversant with Earth affairs, this far from anyplace.”

Like fun we aren’t, Mark thought resentfully. We’re in steady television contact. And some of the smartest people Earth ever produced come here to live—to learn, explore, start a thousand enterprises on a whole new world.

“I remain astonished at your age,” Kamolondo said. “What happened to your parents?”

“They died when a pit collapsed, two years ago. Nobody had suspected, then, that ferralloy cross-braces can change into a weaker crystalline form under Lunar conditions. They left me and my brother and sister. We get along.”

“You were actually allowed to—” Kamolondo clicked his tongue.

“We get along, I say.” Mark wrestled with temper. “Everybody knew we could. Pioneers have always had to grow up fast, haven’t they? Our machinery is automated, we need only nurse it. We attend school, the same as most young people do, via two-way television.” He forced a smile. “Not enough economic surplus yet that the International Lunar Commission can build school buses!”

“You are American, are you not?” Kamolondo asked. “I marvel that American youth can live without cinema and dances.

“Why, the latest entertainment gets beamed straight from Earth. And social life, well, we get to Copernicus town or Keplersburg quite often, hauling in a load of ore.” Mark changed the subject. “Why are you here, sir?”

“To look at what there is,” Kamolondo said. “My people have reached the point where we too would like to exploit the Mooq.”

But this is our home! Mark thought. You don’t exploit your home! No, wait. Kamolondo hadn’t meant it that way. He’d only meant that the Congo wanted to share in developing the frontier and reaping the rewards. Fair enough. But still the word rankled.

Kamolondo stared out into the screens. “I don’t see how you endure such bleakness,” he murmured.

Mark flushed. “Maybe this isn’t much for scenery,” he said, “but you ought to visit one of the mountain ranges, or the big craters. Makes anything on Earth look sick.”

“I have done so,” Kamolondo said. “I continue to prefer an honest forest.”

Everybody to his own taste, Mark thought. He drove on in a silence that thickened. Thank goodness they’d soon be taking this oaf off his hands. Kamolondo was doubtless as happy about that as he was.

They had traveled twelve miles when the catastrophe hit them.

It came with the deadly suddenness of most bad luck on the Moon. At one moment Mark was wondering what Judy would cook for dinner—if His Excellency didn’t like her algaburger with soy sauce, too bad for him—and then thunder exploded. The turtle rocked. A fire-streak slashed before Mark’s vision, dazzling his eyes, stunning his ears. Metal toned. Shock ran through his spacesuit and his bones. Two screens went dark. A pattern of holes gaped black in the wall, and air shrieked outward.

Even as he slammed his faceplate shut, he heard Kamolondo cry something in his mother language, and, “Ah, non! Encore!” A wild part of him wondered why the minister wanted an encore, until he remembered his French. “Oh, no! Again!” The same thing had happened to the turtle as had happened to the Go-Devil. A meteorite shower, hitherto uncharted, must be pounding the Moon.

Mark’s hearing tolled toward silence. He sensed his heartbeat gone loud, smelled with unnatural sharpness the faint tang of ozone and his body in the suit, felt the fabric stiff against him. Outside, dust settled and he identified a tiny new crater, barely visible in the wan light.

He took a firm grip on his wits and tried the car’s radio. Dead. And a helmet unit, necessarily small and simple, couldn’t link with the trans-Lunar microwave system, had indeed no more than a mile of effective range.

He unstrapped himself. “Let’s go,” he said.

“What—what—” Behind the glass, Kamolondo’s face was briefly fluid. Then his lips firmed. He asked in a level voice, “What do you mean?”

“A rock from space landed close by,” Mark said. “Not big, but traveling at miles per second. It scattered chunks of surface material the way a military shell scatters shrapnel. We’re wrecked. If Tom knew, he’d come for us, but he doesn’t and I can’t raise him.” He glanced at the instruments. “We have six miles to go, and dawn is half an hour away.”

Kamolondo did not stir. “Can we make it?” You had to admire how coolly he took the news.

“We’ve got to.” Mark opened the lock.

They were out under Earth and the uncaring stars, in gloom and one faint circle of blue, when Kamolondo said, “I am very sorry to have exposed you to this.”

“Nobody could have known, sir,” Mark said. “One of the chances you take, living here. We expect the big meteorite showers, but little ones on long-period orbits are something else.”

“I realize that. You are young, however, your whole life before you. I would rather have died alone back there.”

“You’re not such a doddering ruin yourself.” Mark managed to laugh. “And who says we can’t beat the sunrise? Come on.”

He set off, with the long bounding stride of a colonist. You can walk fast under low gravity, if you know how. Though the sunrise line would sweep across this part of the Trace in about thirty minutes, it would need another half hour or so to reach Jordan Station. Thus, at six miles per hour, which was vigorous but not exhausting, they’d arrive in time. And afterward the Commission would doubtless buy a new turtle for the man who saved a VIP from a messy death. Maybe throw in a Go-Devil as well.

A curse brought Mark around on his heel. Kamolondo had stumbled. The Congolese got erect, pushed too hard, lost a second before the Moon drew him back to the ground, overbalanced when he hit and fell again. Fear rammed into Mark. Kamolondo didn’t have the reflexes. In two weeks he could barely have learned to handle himself at an ordinary pace. Indoors, at that, without an airtank on his shoulders or tricky constant-volume joints at his knees. “Come on, sir!” Mark urged.

“I am trying.” Kamolondo’s breath was harsh.

He floundered over minutes and miles. Mark sweated, studied the radium-dialed chronometer on the wrist of his suit, clocked them by the kilometer stones. Too slow, too slow. The sun was catching up.

In some years, they could have stood awhile under Lunar daylight. Though the temperature would swiftly rise to the boiling point of water, the suits had thermostatic units and faceplates blocked off ultraviolet light. But now the sun was in a flare period. Lethal radiation, gamma rays, protons, electrons, seethed out of the storms upon it. Nothing less than a “tank,” a vehicle armored in lead and screened by intense magnetic fields, could keep a man alive through such a day.

The tops of the easternmost relay masts began to shine. Kamolondo halted. His face invisible within the helmet, but he stood straight and said calmly, “There is no sense in both of us dying. Proceed.”

For an instant, Mark was ready to obey. Tom, Judy, Dad’s and Mother’s hopes, his own dreams, were they to come to an end for him in the horror of radiation sickness?

But you don’t abandon anyone on the Moon. And Kamolondo was a good joe, trying to do his best for his poor, hurt country. ‘

Mark’s mind sprang toward an answer. He felt suddenly, oddly at peace.

“Listen,” he said. “Relax. Catch your breath. You’re going to need it. We have about three miles left, but the last one is south instead of west.” To strike directly across this shadowland, away from the markers, was to make death certain. “The sun’s not far below the horizon now, but dawnline on the Moon travels eight miles an hour at the equator, a bit less here. So I figure we can rest a little. Then in the last ten or twelve minutes we can do those three miles.”

“A mile . . . one-point-six kilometer . . . Kamolondo’s voice sounded far and strange. “Impossible. You break every athletic record.”

“On Earth! We’re here. Our suits and equipment weigh as much as we do. But the total weight is still a third of what we’d have on Earth, stripped. And no air resistance. Also, running is a lot easier rhythm than what we were doing. Different from back home, of course. You only fall one-sixth as fast. Lean way forward, shove hard with one leg, rise just a bit off the ground. You’ll have plenty of time to recover with the other foot. Watch me.”

Kamolondo did. He tried it himself. Mark was surprised how well he managed, considering how awkward he’d been before. But a dash is, indeed, smoother than a fast walk, on any planet. The only question was whether they both had the endurance. One-sixth gravity or not, they must better the four-minute mile by some twenty percent, across thrice the distance.

Well, well soon know if we can. “Ready? We’re off.”

They ran.

Ghostly glowing, the kilometer stones fell behind, one by one by one. Beyond them and the glow cast by Earth, which seemed to fill the sky with an unreachable loveliness, was utter night. But the sun came striding.

Push, glide, come down, check. Push, glide, come down, check. Impact shivers back, through boots and feet and muscles. Airpumps roar, feeding oxygen to starved cells. Breath grows harsh, mouth dry, pulse frantic. You lurch, lose your balance, he helps you rise and you start again. He trips on an iron fragment and dances crazily, trying not to topple. You count the kilometers creeping past, and then lose count, for blindness has begun to drift across your eyes. You lose yourself, you are nothing but pain and weariness. Still you run!

Turn off here. Now you’re bound straight south, and dawn gains on you. Not far to go. The uppermost crater crags are fiery. A piece of you thinks that you’re close enough to call Tom on your suit radio, but no, he’d need too long to snatch a turtle out. Good-by, Tom. Good-by, Judy. Good-by, universe I wanted to know. A spindle of zodiacal light climbs pearl-colored over the world’s rim. The sun will follow, life-giver, death-giver.

Still you run.

And there is the cave-mouth of the garage. You fling yourself down the ramp. The blessed dark engulfs you, with ten feet of solid matter between you and the solar storm. You collapse on the floor next to your friend, strangling for breath. Only slowly do you understand that you will live.

There is no greater wonder.

They were inside and unsuited, swallowing huge amounts of coffee while Tom and Judy fussed about them, when Kamolondo said, “Mark, in that hour we became brothers.”

It was spoken with such dignity that Mark was ashamed he could find no better answer than, “Aw, gee, nothing like that.”

“You saved me.” Kamolondo raised his head. “Yet more than owing you my life, I want to help you, and your brother and sister. In my position, I have both money and influence. You can come to Earth, study in the finest schools, make the best careers the planet has to offer. I would be proud if you return home with me.

Mark set down his cup. The Jordans stared at each other. Judy and Tom shook their heads slightly. Mark found himself close to laughter.

“Why, thanks,” he said. “But come to Earth?” He swept his hand in a gesture that included the neat little kitchen, the rooms beyond, the subtle and powerful machines working topside, this whole station that was theirs. “Whatever, or—?”